When does the music festival start?
音乐节什么时候开始啊
Soon.
马上了
Hurry on over!
那还不快去
Move it up.
去吧
Really?
真的
Of course.
什么真的假的呀
I love you, Mom!
我爱你 妈妈
Thanks, Dad!
谢谢 谢谢爸爸
Wait,
回来
take your phone with you.
手机
Got it.
好的
Thanks, thanks.
谢谢 谢谢
I'm off!
我走了
Have fun!
玩得高兴啊
Okay.
好
Remember to have lunch!
中午记得吃饭啊
Call if you need anything.
有事打电话
You spoiled her.
都是你惯的
Look at our...
你看我们的
He Lu!
何璐
Thanks, Mr. and Mrs. Li!
谢谢叔叔阿姨
Didn't Liu Siming
这刘思明这小子
get himself
是不是
a chance to show off?
逮着一表现机会了
Thanks to you.
那还不是你给的
Let' go!
冲啊
They actually
你看看啊
got their way.
这还真让她们得逞了
It would be wasteful
票都买了
not to use the tickets.
别浪费了
You just keep spoiling her.
你就惯吧
As long as
何璐妈妈
we're
这
assured the kids are safe,
咱们都知道孩子没事
we can rest easy.
就放心了嘛
They're in the ninth grade,
初三嘛
and be burden with great pressure.
学习压力挺大的
They're exhausted.
够累的
It's beneficial for them
咱们就出来
to unwind occasionally,
偶尔调剂一下
and
这个
balance study with leisure,
劳逸结合
to improve their performances.
促进学习嘛
Since they're already here,
来都来了
let's allow them to enjoy themselves.
就让她们玩吧
By the way, Meng'an,
对了 云阶妈妈
do you two have plans
你们俩今天
to go anywhere else today?
是不是还要出门啊
Yeah.
对
Then we'll stay here
那我们在这儿
and wait for them.
接着等她们
You guys can head home first.
你们先回吧
Okay.
好啊
Thanks for this.
好
It's no big deal.
没事
Don't mention it.
客气呢
We'll head off now.
那我们先走了
Okay.
好
Don't worry.
放心吧
Goodbye.
再见啊
What's wrong?
怎么了
I noticed you
我刚才看你
seemed uncomfortable.
就有点不舒服
Got a bellyache.
肚子疼
Yes, with a dropping sensation.
往下坠得疼
When did it begin?
什么时候开始的
I started feeling unwell
前两天
a couple of days ago.
就有点不太舒服
What should we do now?
那 那现在怎么办
Let's go home first.
先回家
Okay.
好
Hurts so badly?
疼得厉害
It feels like... like I'm bleeding.
好像 好像流血了
Hospital.
上医院
Let's go.
走
We're going to the hospital.
咱们上医院啊
Hang in there.
你坚持一会儿
Be careful.
来
I'm pregnant.
怀孕了
I had a feeling before.
我之前就有预感
What kind of feeling?
预感什么呀
I don't want this baby.
我不想要
Honey,
不是 老婆
we can give it a shot.
我们 可以争取一下
For what?
争取什么呀
Having a second child?
生二胎吗
We shall never
我们千万
rush into any decisions.
不要草率地做决定
Let's think it over.
我们再想想
Meng'an,
梦安
Have you really
这个事
thought it through?
你真的想好了吗
No.
没有
What's your opinion?
你什么想法啊
You want the truth?
说实话吗
I want this baby.
我想要
How is it?
怎么样
It still hurts?
还疼吗
We're almost there.
马上就到
Hold on.
快了
Threatened abortion
你这孕酮低
due to low progesterone.
先兆性流产
Maintain the pregnancy or not?
保胎吗
Maintain.
保
I'll prescribe some medication for you.
好 那我给你们开点药
Look at your girl.
你说这死丫头啊
Everyone else is out except her.
别人都出来就她不出来
She drives me crazy every day.
一天把我气死 你说
Honey,
老婆
on the way back,
一会儿回去的路上
please don't scold Lulu anymore.
你千万别再说璐璐了
Kids these days
现在的孩子呀
are so fragile and rebellious.
又脆弱 又叛逆
If we continue this way,
这样以后
she won't heed our words anymore.
我们很难管的
Fine, I got it.
行了 我知道了
She drives me nuts.
气死人
Hi, Mr. and Mrs. He.
叔叔阿姨好
You just keep playing.
这玩起来没完了
Well, we had to wait
那我们不得
for our favorite band
等我们喜欢的乐队
to finish.
演完啊
When will you
什么时候
be so keen to studying?
学习有这个积极性嘛
Mrs. He,
阿姨
where are my mom and dad?
我爸爸妈妈呢
They've left.
他们走啦
Aren't they going on a long trip?
他们不是出趟远门吗
Your mom asked us to take you
你妈妈让我们把你啊
to your grandma's place.
送到你外婆家去
Thanks, Mrs. He.
谢谢阿姨
Thanks, Mr. He.
谢谢叔叔
Let's get in the car.
上车吧
The calm before the storm.
暴风雨前的宁静
When I get home,
等我回到家
it's bound to be another storm.
肯定又是一阵腥风血雨
So what will you do?
那你怎么办啊
If it comes to it,
实在不行
I'll use my trump card.
我就拿出我的杀手锏
I'll say they
就说他们
only care about my brother, not me.
只管我弟弟不管我
Your parents really trust you.
你爸妈心可真大
They don't even keep an eye on you,
这都不管你
just went back to the hometown.
直接回老家去了
I'm so jealous of you,
真羡慕你啊
dodging a bullet.
躲过一劫
Rest up in the car.
一会儿上车好好休息
Save your energy.
养精蓄锐
You'll need it for the challenges ahead.
一会儿还要面对疾风呢
Good luck.
加油
I'll ride.
我骑车
I didn't ask you.
问你了吗
Let's go.
走
I went to a music festival today.
我今天去那音乐节
So much fun.
可有意思了
If you were there,
你要在的话
you would enjoy it too.
肯定也很喜欢的
Really?
是吗
It was you who brought me
我第一次去音乐节
to my first music festival.
就是你带我去的
Really?
是吗
I recall it now.
我想起来了
That was so long ago.
那得多早以前的事了
Back when your uncle and I
那会儿我和你小姨父
were still dating.
还在谈恋爱呢
Time flies.
时间过得真快
We were so free back then.
那会儿多自由啊
I remember
记得那次
it was my first time seeing a band,
是我第一次看乐队
first time drinking Coke,
第一次喝可乐
first time eating ice cream.
第一次吃冰激凌
Despite getting an earful from my mom,
虽然被我妈训了一顿
it was worth it.
那也值了
Not just you,
何止你被你妈训呢
I was nearly scolded to death too.
我都快被你妈骂死了
You have no idea,
你不知道啊
she's been berating me since I was young,
你妈从小就爱骂我
always wanting to meddle in everything.
什么事都要管
Sometimes
你姥姥 姥爷
even your grandparents don't bother with me;
有时候都不管我吧
it's all your mom.
全都是你妈管
At least you've got grandma spoiling you.
你好歹有外婆宠着你啊
I had it way worse.
那我就太惨了呀
My mom was super strict.
我妈管这么严
My dad didn't have much say
我爸在家
at home.
又没什么话语权
I just hoped my grandparents
我都希望外公外婆
would come
能冲过来
to the rescue.
帮帮我
It shows that back then,
说明当年
what happened to me
在我身上发生的
is now happening to you.
现在都在你身上重演了
My sister really
我姐真是
had a tough time.
真是不容易啊
Looking back,
现在想想
I'm really grateful to your mom.
多亏了你妈
When I was little,
小时候呢
I didn't do well in school.
小姨的成绩不好
Your mom was really worried.
你妈其实特别着急
When she got anxious, she'd scold me.
她一着急她就训我
When she scolded me,
她一训我
I'd doodle all over my textbooks.
我就在课本上乱涂乱画
Later,
结果有一次
your mom found it out.
被你妈发现了
I thought,
完了
"I am done for it",
我想 完了完了完了
and was ready for another lecture,
你妈肯定又要训我了
but instead, she checked the drawings,
结果你妈在那儿看半天
and remarked, "Pretty well,
我妹画得不错嘛
you got some real talent here."
我妹妹是个人才啊
She decided to take me to art classes.
她就带我去学画画
She said, "If academics aren't your thing,
她说你学习不行
then
算了
don't bother with exam,
别考试了
focus on art,
去学美术
and aim for college."
考大学
So every week,
然后她每周呢
she'd take me to
就带着我去
art class.
上那个画画课
It was over an hour's
要坐一个多小时的
bus ride.
公交车
It was tough.
可辛苦了
I was sitting there learning sketching,
我在那儿坐着学素描课
and your mom brought a small chair,
你妈就搬个小椅子
and sat next to me writing news articles
在我边上写新闻稿
without even a table.
连个桌子都没有
Seems like my mom
那看来我妈眼光
had sharp eyes.
还挺好的
She spotted your talent.
发现小姨才华了
I didn't think so back then,
那我当时不觉得呀
I hated her for it.
我还恨她呢
I felt she was taking up
我觉得她占用
my only weekend break.
我仅有的周末休息时间
Now that I think I was pretty silly.
现在想想其实挺傻的哈
I'm really grateful to your mom
多亏你妈
for pushing me back then.
当年逼了我一把
Otherwise,
要不然的话
I would never make it to college.
我也不可能上大学呀
You know,
你知道吧
a lot of my good classmates
小姨以前玩得好的同学
didn't go to college.
好几个都没上大学
Their lives are really tough now.
现在日子过得可苦了
So,
所以
even though I cried a lot back then,
虽然当年气哭了好多回
I'm still really thankful to your mom.
但是还是很谢谢你妈妈
If I hadn't gone to college,
要是我不上大学
I wouldn't have
那我也不可能
ended up in design,
走上设计这条路
and wouldn't have started a business
更不可能跟你小姨父
with your uncle.
一块儿创业
I think uncle
我觉得小姨父
is really a good guy.
可真是好人
He's been so great to you.
他对你真的太好了
I need to find a husband
以后我得按照
as exceptional as my uncle.
小姨父的标准找老公
No, no, no.
别别别
That's really not necessary.
大可不必 大可不必
Just look at me.
你看看我
Now,
现在
I have no freedom at all.
一点自由都没有
Whose fault is that?
怪谁啊
It's all your uncle's fault.
都怪你小姨父
Had an abortion?
做了
How could you let her make it?
你怎么能让她给做了
Not here.
外面 别
Outside.
出去说
Didn't do it?
没做啊
That's great.
太好了
You scared me
吓死我了
to death!
我跟你说
Li Lin.
我给你讲 姐夫
You need to
你要跟姐
talk to sis
好好做做思想工作
seriously.
真的
I'm backing you up.
生孩子的事我是后盾
Listen,
我跟你说
I've figured everything out.
办法我都想好了
I gave Meng'an some money before
之前我不是给姐钱
but she didn't accept it.
但姐不要吗
Now I'll give you the money,
我现在把钱给你
just tell her it's the funds
你就说这是学校
from your school.
给你的经费
So...
你就
No need for money.
不用钱了
Meng'an has already decided
梦安已经决定
to keep the baby.
保胎了
What?
保胎
You're amazing, Li Lin.
你太厉害了 姐夫
Well done!
太好了
I said you should have the baby.
我就说要生嘛
Don't you lie to me, okay?
真的要保胎 姐夫
You're something else.
你可以啊你
You can even convince Meng'an
姐的思想工作
to change her mind.
你都能做通
I see you usually
我看你平时在她面前
listening to her every word.
言听计从的
You're quite persuasive.
说话还挺好使
It's not me convincing her.
不是我劝她的
She figured it out
是她自己啊
herself.
想通了
She wants the baby, that's what matters.
那不管 只要她愿意生
Li Lin,
姐夫
you need to keep a close eye on her,
你可得把她盯紧了
otherwise, she may change her mind
别到时候她突然又变了
and seek an abortion.
一不留神把手术给做了
No, no, no.
不不不
What if she wakes up and regrets it?
万一醒了呢 又后悔
I'll go and check.
我去看看
No, no, no.
别别别
Get back.
你回来你
Why are you so worked up?
干吗那么激动啊
It's too early to be this happy.
现在高兴得还太早
Some situation
有些情况它
is a bit complicated.
就是 它有点复杂
It's just having a baby.
不就是生个孩子吗
It's just raising a child.
不就是养孩子
I'm
我跟你说了 我
backing you up.
后盾
Can you stop patting me?
你能不能不要再拍我了
Can you let me finish?
你能不能听我说完
Just muttering back-up...
后盾 后盾的
and speaking so loudly.
声音还那么大
Alright.
好好好
Go ahead.
你说
Meng'an had a threatened miscarriage.
梦安啊 她是先兆流产
The doctor says she needs to
大夫让她现在呢
stay in the hospital for observation.
留院观察
She just got that
这不刚打的那个
shot to keep the baby.
保胎针吗
Got it?
知道了吧
So we don't know yet
所以后面怎么样
what will happen next.
还不知道呢
Nothing to be pleased about.
这高兴什么呀
Perhaps we
也 也许
want the baby,
我们想生
yet the God doesn't permit.
老天不允许呗
You should stay optimistic.
那你也要保持乐观
We've already made a big step,
咱们已经走了一大步了
from firmly not wanting the baby,
从开始坚决不生
to trying to keep it, right?
到现在开始保胎对吧
Didn't Mengxin go through the same thing?
心心不也一样吗
She's expecting her second child.
都怀第二个了
When she was pregnant with our first child,
第一个时候
we faced numerous challenges.
遇到各种困难
The doctors said the same, sometimes,
医生也那么说
the progesterone level is too low,
一会儿孕酮低了
sometimes too high,
一会儿孕酮高了
which frightened us
把我们吓唬得
greatly.
深一脚浅一脚
But wasn't xiongxiong born healthy?
熊熊生出来不好好的
Yeah,
对啊
I recall that
你这么一说我想起来了
Meng'an
就是梦安
also experienced threatened miscarriage
在怀云阶的时候啊
when she's carrying Yunjie.
也说她是先兆流产
So,
所以说
get the treatment,
该治疗治疗
and keep the baby.
该保胎保胎
As long as sis has changed her mind,
只要姐思想转变了
that's a good thing.
那就是好事
So,
那就
let it be.
顺其自然吧
Li Lin,
姐夫
how did you
你怎么样
convince her?
给姐把思想工作做通了
I tried to get her to the company
我之前约谈她到公司
to work as a consultant
想让她给我们当个顾问
and earn some extra money.
赚点外快
But she wouldn't agree.
她死活都不答应
It wasn't me convincing her.
不是我做的思想工作
She made the decision.
是你姐自己想明白的
But as for how she came to that
但至于怎么想明白的
I...
我
I don't know.
我也不太好说
Haowen,
老贾
how did you know?
你是怎么知道的
Mengxin told you that?
心心跟你说的
Yes...
对
You know
心心这个人啊
Mengxin
你是了解的
can't keep secrets.
那个心里藏不住事
She's very straightforward.
特别简单
Is that so?
是吗
You've given yourself away.
穿帮了吧
You just said
你刚才是说
you advised Meng'an.
你劝过梦安
Is that what you said?
是不是你说的
Still making things up
还编
Come on.
真是
Answer me,
我就问你
when you said that
你说这话的时候
did Meng'an scold you?
梦安没骂你啊
Did she give you an earful?
没镇压你啊
Of course she did.
镇压了
Well, I'm willing to give it a try
那我也愿意试一试
for the sake of the family.
为了这个家
Where there's a will, there's a way.
有志者事竟成
That's my motto.
那是我的座右铭
Haowen,
老贾
sorry for troubling you.
让你操心了
In this regard,
就这一点
I really need to learn from you.
我还真得向你学习学习
You're right.
说得没错
Where there's a will, there's a way.
有志者事竟成
That's so true.
说太好了
Are you hungry?
你饿了吧
No.
我不饿
No, you are hungry.
你饿了
Come on, let's grab something.
你饿了 咱俩吃东西
I'm really not.
我真不饿
You're hungry.
你饿
Let's go.
走吧 走吧 走吧
Why must I be hungry?
我为什么要饿呢
I've already eaten.
我吃过饭了
How do you feel? Better?
感觉怎么样 好点没
-Not that much. -Much better.
一般吧 好多了
Not that much?
一般
Check for a fever.
看有没有烧
It is gone.
不烧了
See?
你看
It's fine.
好了
Come on, Zhenzhen.
来 真真过来
Good, fever's gone.
还行 退烧了
What's wrong?
你咋了这是
I don't know.
不知道
On my way.
来了
I open the door.
妈妈去开门啊
Why aren't you happy?
咋不高兴啊
On my way.
来了
Dr. Yu.
俞医生
Miss Chen.
陈小姐
How are the children?
孩子们怎么样
Has the fever gone down?
烧退了吗
Much better.
好多了
I made some rice soup.
我熬了点粥
They have just recovered
她们病刚好
and should avoid spicy food.
不能吃太辛辣的
It's best to eat something light.
吃点清淡的吧
No need.
不用了 不用了
They've already eaten.
她们吃过了
Already?
吃过了
Have you eaten yet?
你是不是没吃饭啊
I...
我
I
你看
knew it.
我一猜就是
You were so busy looking after the kids
光顾着照顾孩子
that you skipped a meal.
自己没吃吧
You need to eat something.
你得吃点
Then you can have energy
吃饱了才有力气
to care for them.
照顾孩子嘛
Okay, thank you.
行 谢谢你啊
You're welcome.
不用客气
Thanks.
谢谢
I'm leaving.
我走了
Bye.
拜拜
Haowen,
浩文
since I became
我自打跟你
your brother-in-law,
做了亲戚之后
the places we eat at
这吃饭的地儿
become worse and worse.
是越来越随意了
Come on,
来
Li Lin.
姐夫
Let's have a toast
咱俩碰一个啊
to celebrate
为今儿这事
today's happiness.
庆祝一下
Cheers.
干杯
Li Lin.
姐夫
I just returned from another city today
我今儿从外面才回来
and learned that Meng'an underwent surgery,
我听说姐做手术
which had me worried.
给我急的
I didn't dare ask Xin about it,
我又不敢问心心
for she would fall out
她现在
with anyone who brought up
谁跟她说生孩子
the topic of childbirth.
她跟谁翻脸
Why?
为什么
isn't Mengxin
心心不是
also expecting a second child now?
也要生二胎了吗
I'm really hard at home.
我现在在家里我太难了
Really.
真的
She's fixated on it now.
她现在钻了牛角尖了
She feels
她就觉着
that I tricked her into having a child.
是我骗她生的孩子
But I really want
但我确实想
to have a second child.
生孩子
Parents also helped.
爸妈也助了一臂之力
Who doesn't want
谁不愿意家里
a lively home
热热闹闹的
with an extra little baby.
多出一个宝贝呢
Mengxin is right,
心心说得没错
it is you who want a second baby.
那确实是你想生吧
So I am.
我就是想生啊
I'm at home
所以我在家
being her servant,
给她当孙子呀
I'll do whatever she wants.
她怎么样我都行
Once our baby
只要咱家孩子
is born,
生下来以后
I'll kneel and bow to her,
我给她跪那儿磕一大头
and call her grandma.
我把她叫姑奶奶
Oh my,
天哪
your family's is really mixed up.
你们家这辈分真乱
When we were
就上回咱们俩
drinking last time,
喝酒的时候啊
you were so happy
你一听说有二胎了
to hear about the second child.
那 多高兴啊
Today, hearing this
今天这么一说
I really think you
我觉得你确实是
are not easy.
挺不容易的
Let me ask you,
问你呀
with a second child coming,
要二胎了
what preparations
咱们
do we need to make?
得做一些什么准备啊
Or,
或者说
are there any changes?
她们有什么变化
Lin,
变化 姐夫
there are huge changes.
那变化太大了
It's like a woman
那就是一个女人
becoming a fierce tiger.
变成了母老虎那么大
What fierce tiger?
什么母老虎啊
Meng'an didn't behave this way
那梦安生云阶的时候
when carrying Yunjie.
没事啊
It wasn't like this.
不是这样啊
Li Lin.
姐夫
I'm speaking the truth.
我说的是句句实话
Even though they are sisters,
你别看她们姐妹俩
and born of the same mother.
是一个妈生的
Their temperaments are very different.
但性格截然不同
You know,
你知道我现在这
my back, my waist
这背上 这腰上
and my shoulders
左膀子上
and my arms are bruised
什么右臂被她掐得
because of her.
青一块紫一块的
But I withstood it all.
但是我认了呀
I accept it.
我认
I believe where there's a will, there's a way.
我就觉着有志者事竟成
Is that really true?
真 真假的呀
Meng'an wouldn't do that.
我们家梦安不会
Li Lin.
姐夫
Mengxin is about to give birth.
我们家心心快生了
I'm sure
我肯定
my baby will be born before yours.
孩子生在你前面
So as someone who's been through it,
那我作为过来人
I need to tell you something.
我得跟你说一句话
Stop it.
你打住吧
Where there's a will, there's a way.
有志者事竟成嘛
Wrong.
错
Pretend to be weak to stay safe.
装   保平安
I can handle this.
这我行
Wanwan, Zhenzhen,
婉婉 真真
Dr. Yu sent us some rice soup,
俞辰叔叔送的粥
who wants it?
你们喝不喝
Me.
喝
Come quickly.
快过来
Alright, one bowl each.
好 一人一碗
This is mine.
这是我的
Here, Zhenzhen.
来 真真
Thank you, Mom.
谢谢妈妈
You're awake.
醒了
What time is it?
几点了
It's already dark.
天都黑了
I...
我这
Did I sleep
我是不是睡了
for a really long time?
特长时间呀
I feel like I slept very deeply.
我觉得我睡得特沉
Very deeply.
特别沉
Really?
是吧
That's great
特别好
I've never seen you
我都没见过你
sleep so well.
睡得那么好
Is that so?
是吗
Would you like some water?
喝口水
No, thanks.
不喝
Some fruit I've just washed?
刚洗的水果 你吃点
I don't want any.
不想吃
Alright.
行
Does it still hurt?
还疼不疼了
It doesn't hurt anymore.
不疼了
Much better.
好多了
The medicine is quite effective.
药还挺管用
You still have a good constitution.
还是你身体好啊
Right?
是吧
I
我
wonder,
问你啊
why did you suddenly
你是怎么突然之间
decide to keep the baby?
就决定了呢
I don't know.
不知道啊
There...
这
has to be a reason.
总得要有个理由啊
You
你
just make up an excuse.
你编一下
An excuse?
编一下
Let me make up
我想想
an excuse.
编一个
I...
我
Let me think.
想想啊
Actually, it's because on the way here,
其实就是来的路上
when I looked at you
我看着你的时候
I suddenly felt quite sorry for you.
突然挺心疼你的
I feel
我是觉得
that I've lived more than forty years,
我活到四十多岁
and it's been quite smooth.
一直挺顺风顺水的
I haven't met any major setbacks
工作上
at work.
没有什么大的波折
And my parents are still alive.
家庭上也都父母健在
I'm not like you,
我跟你不太一样
I haven't lost any loved ones.
没有经历过亲人离世
So...
所以
However, when I had the bellyache,
但是我肚子疼的时候
I was extremely
是真的
frightened.
很慌
I thought,
我就在想
if I lost this baby,
要是我这孩子没了
I...
我
No, no, no.
不不不
This is not a good excuse.
这 这个编得不好
Let me organize my thoughts.
我 我再组织一下
Otherwise, just
要不然你就
consider me a mammal.
还当我是个哺乳动物吧
A
一个
high-level mammal.
高级的哺乳动物
A female,
雌性
mammal.
兔崽子
Okay?
行吗
That's a pretty good excuse.
编得挺好的
The logic is clear.
逻辑很清楚
Really?
真的
But do you think this decision
但 但我这决定会不会
might be a bit hasty?
会不会有点草率啊
Not hasty.
不草率
It's really good.
特别好
I feel really happy.
我特别开心
Really?
真的吗
Really.
真的
When you were asleep just now,
就你刚才睡着了
I thought a lot.
我想了很多
I thought when Yunjie
我想到了云阶
was just born.
刚出生那会儿
It was fifteen years ago, right?
十五年以前了吧
When she was born,
她刚生出来
she was that tiny,
就那么大
less than 3 kilos.
六斤都不到
That tiny girl,
那小小的
her head flopping gently to one side,
脑袋软软地耷拉一边
her skin delicate
皮肤薄薄的
and wrinkled -
皱皱巴巴
I was afraid to even hold her,
你让我抱我都不敢抱
for fear of hurting her.
我怕给她弄坏了
Yet, I really adored her.
但是我是真的喜欢
In the blink of an eye,
你看你一转眼
she's fourteen,
这孩子都十四岁了
right?
是吧
She's now in the ninth grade,
初三了
and has learned to deceive us with friends.
都学会组团骗人了
Of course it's not her fault,
组团骗人不是她啊
it must be Liu Siming.
一定是刘思明那小子
He's full of tricks.
他 一肚子坏水
And what did he say?
还说什么
A protector of flowers?
护花使者
What flowers is he protecting?
他护什么花
What kind of protector is he?
他是什么者
He's just a little brat,
他就是个臭小子
still wet behind the ears.
乳臭未干
And don't forget about me,
再说了 还有我
I'm her dad,
我是她爸
and I'm still around.
我还在呢
right?
对吧
Yes.
在呢
In two years,
你说过两年
Yunjie will really have
咱云阶是真的有
a protector of flowers.
护花使者了
That's for sure.
那肯定的呀
At that time,
那个时候
where will I be?
那我在哪儿啊
I'll have to step aside.
我得靠边站啊
Think about my dad.
你想想我爸
It's too scary.
太可怕了
I still have to
我还是得对
be good to my father-in-law.
对老丈人他好点
He's had a tough time.
他太不容易了
Can I go home once I am done
我是不是点完这瓶药
with this bottle of medicine?
就能回家了
The doctor didn't say you can leave.
大夫没说能回家
Can you ask for me?
那你去问问啊
Okay,
我去问问
I'll go ask.
好 我去问问
Such a daughter slave.
女儿奴
♪Come on♪
来来来
♪Closer♪
来来来 来来来
♪Listening to me♪
来来来 来来来 来来来
How much have you drunk?
这是喝了多少酒啊
What's going on?
发什么疯呢
Xin,
老婆
I have some great news to share,
我跟你说有个大喜事
a major celebration in our family.
咱们家的大喜事
All this fuss.
一惊一乍的
What's the news?
什么大喜事啊
Let me tell you...
我跟你说啊
Forget it.
算了吧
You'd yell at me if I say it.
说了你会骂我的
Who cares
爱说不说
whether you speak or not?
谁爱听似的
Every day
一天天的
you drink,
喝酒
socializing,
应酬
out with some shady friends
肯定又跟哪帮狐朋狗友
wasting time.
出去鬼混去了
What serious matter could there be?
能有什么正经事
Honey,
老婆
hanging out with shady friends
跟狐朋狗友鬼混
isn't a big deal.
那叫天大的喜事
This is a big deal.
我这个是天大的喜事
I'm telling you,
我跟你说
if I tell you the news,
我这个喜事要告诉你
you'll think I'm the hero in our family.
你觉着我是咱家的功臣
I've done something great, honey.
我立了大功了 媳妇
Really.
真的
It's a very happy event.
特别开心的喜事
I'm ready.
我准备好了
Go ahead.
你说吧
I really can't tell you.
我真的不能跟你说
Honey.
媳妇
I have to keep my secret.
我要藏住我的秘密
I really can't...
我真的不能
Get out.
不说 滚滚滚 滚
To where?
滚哪儿去啊
Go sleep in the study.
滚出去睡书房
So you won't snore and disturb me
省得喝完酒打呼噜
while I'm trying to sleep.
吵我睡觉
Why should I sleep in the study?
我为什么要睡书房
If you won't share the news,
你不是不说吗
then get out.
不说就滚
Fine,
行
my wife told me to leave,
我的老婆让我滚
so I will.
我就滚
I'll leave.
我滚
Why are you still here?
滚 又干吗
Don't you want to know this news?
不想听啊
Don't want to.
不想
Don't regret it.
你别后悔啊
No regrets.
不后悔
Really, don't regret it.
真别后悔啊
Alright, I can't keep
但是我还是憋不住
it a secret anymore.
想跟你说啊
Let me tell you, honey.
我告诉你 媳妇
Go ahead.
说
What are you packing?
你这收拾啥呢
Yunjie didn't bring anything.
云阶 什么都没带
She has class on Monday.
礼拜一还得上课呢
So hurry up and pack it
那你赶快收好
and send it to her.
给她送一趟吧
That'll be suspicious.
送一趟 那不穿帮了吗
Gosh, we're supposed to be in the hometown.
咱俩在老家呢 是吧
Yes.
对呀
Why don't we ask Mengxin to deliver it?
那要不叫梦心送一趟
Haowen said
浩文说这个事
it's best not to let Mengxin know.
最好别让梦心知道
She's very sensitive about
她现在对生二胎
having a second child.
这个事情很敏感
How about calling
那要不然你给老贾
Haowen?
打个电话
To have his driver make a trip.
让他司机跑一趟
It will work.
可以
I'll call him.
我跟他说
How long do we need to
这个事
keep it a secret?
咱们得瞒多久啊
We'll have to tell her sooner or later.
你看早晚得跟她说
First make sure the pregnancy is stable.
先把胎保住吧
If, unfortunately, we can't,
万一保不住
it'll all be in vain.
不就都空欢喜一场
Alright.
好
We'll tell her and mom when the time comes.
妈那边 到时候一起说
Be sure to remind Haowen
你嘱咐一句老贾啊
to keep it to himself.
让他千万别跟别人说
For now, this should stay between us three.
这事 就咱仨知道
Alright.
好
Hello.
喂
Haowen.
浩文啊
Will you come back for dinner?
你回不回来吃饭呢
An went to the hospital?
安安去医院了
Mom went to the hospital?
我妈去医院了
What's wrong?
什么病啊
Grandpa,
外公
can I use your phone?
手机借我用一下呗
Dad.
爸
Mom.
喂 妈
Yunjie.
云阶啊
Why are you at home?
你怎么在家呀
Aren't you going to your aunt's house?
你不去大姑家了吗
Well,
那个
we ran into some trouble.
遇到点事啊
Honey,
老公啊
Yunjie is on the phone.
云阶来电话了
I'll come back to find you later.
那我一会儿回去找你们
Don't come back for now.
你 你先别回来
Stay at your grandmother's place for now.
你 你先住你外婆家吧
Yunjie,
云阶
tell them to come back.
叫他们回来
Grandpa wants you to come back.
外公叫你们回来
No, no, you can't come back.
别别 不能回 不能回
You can't come back
不能回 不能回
An,
安安哪
you had a viral cold, right?
你不是病毒性感冒吗
Just rest at home.
你就在家好好歇着
You might spread it to us.
回来传染全家呢
Yes.
是
Look, I'm still coughing.
你看我这还咳嗽呢
Yunjie, we don't come home for now.
云阶 先不回家啊
Severe condition.
太辛苦了
Alright then.
这样啊
Yunjie,
云阶
behave good at your grandmother's place.
在外婆家 你听话啊
I'll bring the backpack
那书包
to you later.
我一会儿给你送过去
Dad,
老爸
mom has a viral cold,
老妈这是病毒性感冒
wear a mask
你戴个口罩
or you'll catch it too.
不然传染给你了
Alright, alright.
好 好好好
I'll wear a mask too,
妈一会儿也戴个口罩
and won't spread it to Dad.
不要传染你爸
Yunjie,
那个 云阶啊
Stay at grandma's house
你乖乖地
and act good for a few days,
在外婆家住几天
and I'll come to get you once feel better.
等妈好了就去接你
Okay, take care of yourself.
行 那你照顾好自己啊
Alas,
这
I just finished teaching her not to lie,
刚教完孩子不要撒谎
and here I am lying.
我这就撒谎
Why did my mom
你说我妈也是的
lie like this?
撒这谎干吗呀
I have to cover for her.
我还得帮她圆
It...
这 这
It's not lying, it's...
这不算撒谎 这叫
hiding part of the truth.
隐瞒一部分事实
What about the part that's fabricated?
那虚构那一部分呢
Old people's lie isn't seen as lying.
老人撒谎不算撒谎
Could it be
我妈该不会是
that my mom knows I'm pregnant?
知道我怀了吧
Haowen.
老贾
When Haowen
这老贾
will
什么时候嘴上
ever learn to keep a secret?
能有个把门的
He's driving me crazy.
气死我了
Mengxin is here.
梦心来了
Move aside.
起开
Hi there.
姐夫
What's meant to come will come.
该来的都得来啊
Sis,
姐
Xin,
心心啊
you're in for a tough time.
你这是要遭罪了呀
What can I say.
你说说你
Don't cry.
不哭 不哭
There's no suffering.
不遭罪 不遭罪
Well,
那啥
Haowen didn't come with you?
老贾没跟你一块来呀
He's outside.
来了 在外头
Be good.
乖啊
Don't cry.
不哭 不哭
Why the sigh?
你叹什么气呀
Li Lin.
姐夫
I'm so disappointed in you
我对你太失望了
Haowen.
老贾
Even though I'm your brother-in-law,
虽然我是你姐夫
you're a few years older than me,
但是你比我长几岁
but you shouldn't lie to me.
可是你不能骗我啊
I'm not lying, Li Lin.
我没骗你 姐夫
This is good news.
这是喜事
Good news should be shared.
喜事高兴要分享
Can't secretly
不能闷在我自己
enjoy it
一个人心里
to myself.
偷着乐
What do you think?
你说呢
What about Mom?
那咱妈那儿
Did you tell her too?
是不是也是你说的
I didn't say anything
我没说
You didn't?
你没说
I really didn't.
我真没说
Then who did?
那谁说的
Xin told her.
心心说的
She can't keep a secret.
她心里存不住事
Definitely she.
肯定是她说的
Again?
又是心心
Poor Xin,
你家心心啊
I feel sorry for her.
是真可怜哪
She has to
什么事
shoulder all the blame
都得让她
by herself.
自己一个人背锅
Li Lin,
姐夫啊
let me tell you,
我跟你讲哈
this morning
今儿早上
I came to help you
我来帮你们
prepare the maternity meal.
做那个孕妇餐
I can manage without your assistance.
不用你帮忙 我也会做
It's not the same.
我这不一样
I've got a second baby.
我这二胎
I'm more experienced.
我经验更丰富
Really?
真的
How so?
怎么
A second baby is different?
二胎还不一样啊
Of course it is.
当然不一样啊
How different?
怎么不一样
It requires more balanced nutrition,
要营养更均衡
and a more sensible combination.
那个 搭配更合理
You should take notes.
你学着点啊
You're pretty articulate.
你挺有词啊
Of course.
当然
You're a knowledgeable person.
你是个知识分子
You don't have to work today.
今天不用干活
Alright.
行
Show me
你做给我看看
what you can do.
我看看你多能耐啊
Cutting grapes
这剪个葡萄
like this?
怎么剪成这样
The stems
这
are still on.
梗还在
Li Lin,
姐夫 我跟你讲
Xin is really picky.
我们家心心可讲究了
Why cut the grapes?
这葡萄为什么要剪呢
If I tear them by hand,
我要用手一撕
she won't eat them if they're torn.
撕破了她就不吃
Hard to please.
难伺候
It's even worse now.
现在更严重
You know?
知道吗
So it's not easy for you.
所以说你是不容易
Learn from this.
学着点啊
Li Lin.
我的大姐夫
That's good.
挺好
When you're available,
你没事
come by our place more often
常来我们家坐坐
and cook sometimes.
也做做饭
I could use a break.
我也歇歇
No problem.
没问题
As long as sis is willing to have the kid.
只要姐肯生
I'm studying game strategies.
干啥呀 我研究棋谱呢
Got some good news.
有个好消息
Want to hear it?
想不想听
What's the good news?
啥好消息啊
Guess.
猜
Stocks went up.
股票涨了
Pension and social insurance increased.
退休金 劳保又涨了
Wrong.
再猜
Your dance partner
你那个舞伴
is back.
老韩头 回来了
Button it.
去
So,
那
what's the good news?
还有啥高兴事啊
This is interesting.
真有意思
You know why Meng'an
你知道梦安
hasn't shown up
两个礼拜没露脸
for two weeks?
因为什么
Isn't she sick?
她不病了吗
You believe that?
这你也信
That's what you told me.
不你说的吗
Alright.
行了
What's going on? Hurry up.
啥事啊 赶紧说吧
I'm dying of curiosity.
急死我了
Meng'an
梦安
Has...
有啦
What?
有啥啦
Meng'an is...
梦安有啦
What is she having?
啥玩意有了
A second baby.
二胎
Are you serious?
真的假的
Meng'an is having a second baby.
梦安二胎
Come on.
来来 来来来
Such a big deal.
这么大的事
How could you hide this from me?
你怎么能瞒着我呢
The pregnancy was unstable.
这不是胎一直还不稳吗
But you should have
那你也应该
told me right away.
第一时间告诉我啊
I'm your sister.
我是你亲妹妹
Yeah.
对对对 对
My bad.
我错了 我错了
Don't worry.
你这情况没事的啊
It's similar to my early pregnancy.
跟我孕早期差不多
Just take some progesterone.
吃点孕酮就好
How old are you?
你多大岁数
How old am I?
我多大岁数啊
It's not the same.
那能一样吗
It'll be fine, trust me.
肯定没问题 你信我的
I'm more experienced
我这二胎怀得比你早
with the second baby.
比你有经验
Later
回头啊
I'll take you to see
我带你去找我那个
my attending doctor.
主治大夫
We can go for
咱俩可以一块儿
a check-up together.
去做产检
No need.
不去
Your hospital is far and expensive.
你那医院又贵又远的
I can just find
我这就在家附近
a public hospital nearby.
找个公立医院就行了
It's fine.
没事
I have plenty of money in my medical card.
我那医疗卡里钱多着呢
I'll come pick you up later.
回头我来接你
You can leave me
你那些孕妇装什么的
those maternity clothes.
倒是可以留给我
Sure.
行
I'll buy you new ones.
我给你买新的
Are you
你说
trying to copy me?
你是不是在学我
Trying to follow in my footsteps?
想步我后尘
Actually,
事实上
I'm following your footsteps.
是步了你后尘的
When we were kids,
小时候呢
I was always
总是我追在你
chasing after you,
屁股后头跑
wearing your
你穿剩的衣服呀
hand-me-downs.
都留给我穿
Now I will revenge.
现在我要报复回来
I'm not buying you maternity clothes,
孕妇装不给你买
you can wear my old ones.
你就穿我剩下的
Alright.
行
What else do you have left?
你还有什么剩下的
Leave everything to me.
都留给我
Coming!
来了啊
Coming.
来了来了来了
Look.
看
These grapes today
今儿这葡萄
are big and round.
又大又圆
If pregnant women eat grapes,
人都说孕妇多吃葡萄
their babies will be fair-skinned.
生的孩子白
Is Haowen the one cooking?
老贾做饭呢
Yes, he'll prepare a pregnancy breakfast.
他说要给你做孕妇早餐
A pregnancy breakfast?
孕妇早餐啊
It should be rich and varied.
那可得丰富点
Yes.
对
Let him do it.
让他做
Li Lin.
姐夫
Aren't you going to help?
你不去帮忙啊
I'll go help.
我去帮忙啊
I'll learn from it.
我 我学习学习
Today is my visiting time, right?
今天是我的探视时间吧
I'm in the basement.
我在地库里呢
Send the kids down to me.
你把孩子们给我送下来
Lv,
小吕
I'll take a quick nap.
我眯瞪会儿啊
I drank too much last night.
昨晚上喝多了
Wake me up when the kids come down.
待会儿孩子下来叫我啊
Okay, Mr. Yu.
好的 于总
Sister,
妹妹
last time you brought the toys,
上次就是你带的玩具
can you let me bring it this time?
这次可以让姐姐带吗
No, I want to bring this one.
不要 我想带这个
Last time, you already brought it.
上次就是你带的
You can't bring this one today.
不可以带这个了
I'm tired of it already.
上次我都玩腻了
I must play with this one.
必须玩这个了
I haven't gotten tired of this one.
这个我没玩腻
I want to bring this one.
我要带这个
I must play with this one.
必须玩这个
I'm not tired of it yet.
我还没玩腻呢
I want to play with this one.
我要玩这个
Alright, alright.
好了 好了
Stop arguing.
不吵了 不吵了
Put the toys down.
把玩具放下来
Let's go downstairs.
咱们下去了
You've just recovered from illness.
这病刚好
Don't eat just anything.
不能瞎吃东西
Be good at grandpa's house.
去爷爷家要听话
Time to go.
走
Let's go.
走了 走了
Hi, Ms. Chen.
陈小姐
Hello, Dr. Yu.
俞医生
Hi, Dr. Yu.
俞辰叔叔好
How are you two princesses feeling?
怎么样 两个小公主
Any better?
身体好点了吧
Much better.
好多了
Mr. Yu.
于总
The kids has come downstairs.
孩子下来了
Hurry.
不是 快
Come closer.
过过过 过去
See you then.
那赶紧走吧
Don't keep Grandpa waiting.
别让爷爷等着
Put on your backpacks.
把书包背上
Okay.
好
Here.
来
Don't eat too many cold things.
少吃凉的啊
Be good.
要乖
Okay.
好
Daddy's here.
爸爸来了
I missed you so much.
想死我了
Daddy bought new clothes for you.
爸爸给你们买的新衣服
Can't give them to you now.
现在不能给你们
You'll get them
那个先给下一水
after washing.
完了再穿
Say goodbye to mommy.
跟妈妈再见吧
Goodbye, Mommy.
妈妈再见
Goodbye, Dr. Yu.
俞辰叔叔再见
Goodbye.
再见
Bye.
拜拜 拜拜
Fasten your seat belts.
安全带系上啊
Let's go.
去吧
Close the door.
关门
What's wrong? Feeling unwell?
怎么了 不舒服啊
It's fine.
没事
Just an old problem.
老毛病犯了
Low blood sugar.
低血糖
Luckily, I bought a box of chocolates.
正好买了盒巧克力
Quick, eat one.
赶紧吃一个
Thank you.
谢谢啊
Giving chocolates?
怎么还送巧克力呀还
Keep them all.
都给你吧
Just in case.
以防万一
The kids are gone.
孩子走了
Hurry up and rest upstairs.
赶紧上楼休息吧
This is ginseng.
这是人参
I didn't know until I saw it.
真是不看不知道啊
Quite a shock.
一看吓一跳
Jia Haowen really
贾浩文这孩子是
brings us a lot of things.
没少往这儿拿东西啊
When does he ever come empty-handed?
他哪次来空手啊
And there's more.
还有呢
That's enough.
行了 别拿了
You need to leave some.
你总得留点啊
What will the kids eat when they're back?
要不孩子们回来吃啥呀
Right, soft-shelled turtles.
对了对了 甲鱼甲鱼
Take out the turtles.
把甲鱼捞出来
I got an idea.
我有个想法
You know,
那个
Xin is pregnant
你看心心肚子里
with one child.
怀着一个
An is pregnant with one child.
安安肚子里怀着一个
Could
能不能
the baby in An's womb
让安安肚子里那个
take the surname Xu?
姓许啊
Come over.
过来
42 degrees.
四十二度
It's popular now,
人家现在就流行
two good families
两好并一好
merging into one.
两家并一家
Each child takes one of their parents' surnames.
两个孩子一人一家姓
Would Li Lin agree to this?
那人家李临能愿意吗
This...
你这
Well,
那
that's just what Li Lin's family does.
李临他们家就这样啊
Do you remember
你还记得
his eldest brother-in-law?
他那个大姐夫吗
Doesn't he have the surname Ouyang?
不是姓欧阳吗
He named his child Huahua,
他生那孩子叫华华
Huahua's surname is Li.
华华就姓李
Yes.
对呀
The child of Ouyang
欧阳
can't even take the surname Ouyang,
生的孩子不能姓欧阳
just because Lin's sister insisted
他大姐
the child take their family's surname, Li.
非让姓他们家的姓 李
Do you think she
人家老李家的孩子
would agree
他大姐
to their child
会同意老李家的孩子
taking the surname Xu?
姓老许家的姓吗
His eldest sister
他大姑姐
would be furious.
不得跟你拼命啊
Don't even think about it.
你可别想了
I think
我觉得
Li Lin might agree.
李临能同意
He is reasonable.
李临知书达理
Is his eldest sister
他大姐
reasonable?
是那知书达理的人吗
That's enough.
行了
We can give it a try.
试试呗
Trying won't work.
试试吗都不行
Turtles, my precious,
老甲呀
reveal yourself now.
老甲你在哪儿啊
Who's calling me?
谁想我呢
My dad, it turns out.
爸
Missing me that much?
谁那么想我啊
Welcome back.
回来啦
I'm looking for the turtles actually.
我找甲鱼哪
Take a rest,
来来来
I'll catch them.
给我 给我 给我
Leave it to him.
让他干 让他干
Come on.
你看看 你看看
Leave it to me.
我来 我来 快来
Is there any?
有没有
Haowen,
浩文
Why did you buy so many things again?
你怎么又买这么多东西
What are you doing?
干啥去啊
There's no need to rush.
那不用着急拿
Won't miss.
又丢不了
I'll look for it.
我来找吧
Chat with your daughter.
陪你姑娘说说话吧
Where are the turtles?
甲鱼在哪儿呢
Xin,
心心
Mom.
妈
How are you?
怎么样
I'm doing well.
我挺好的
Why these items
我说这些个东西
look a bit
怎么看着
familiar?
有点眼熟呢
Aren't these items you and Haowen
不都是你和浩文
brought back?
拿回来的吗 爸
Indeed.
是哈
No.
不行
Keep it, Dad.
拿着 爸 拿着
We are families, there's no need.
干啥呀 都认识
Just keep it.
没事